Anurag Ambuja

Data Engineer



Professional with around 10+ years of experience in Software Development, Automation & Bug Fixing in Retail, Networking and Banking Sector.

Currently working as Big Data Engineer with 5+ years of extensive experience in Big Data Ecosystem.

• <u>Linkedin</u> • <u>Medium</u> • <u>Github</u> • *Gurgaon, India* • +91-8800442797 • anurag.ambuja@gmail.com

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Lead Data Engineer, IHS Markit

09/2020 -

Gurugram, Haryana

Role & Responsibilities

- Requirement Gathering, Analysis and designing technical Solutions. Do effort estimation and planning
- Implement the business requirement on BigQuery

Lead Data Engineer, Dunnhumby

01/2019 - 09/2020

Gurugram, Haryana

Role & Responsibilities

- Analyse problem statement and Design/Modify Data Lake Solution for Transactional and Dimensional Data.
- Migration of existing structured data from RDBMS database, flat files or SAS dataset to Hadoop/Hive using Sqoop or Spark.
- Writing spark job to compute aggregated data for faster processing of data using Pyspark.
- Use Spark API over Cloudera Hadoop YARN to perform analytics data on Hive.
- Involved in converting Hive/SQL queries into Spark Transformation using Spark dataframes and Python.
- Parsing different file formats like xml, json and converting it into structured format using python.
- To develop Hive programs to cleanse and parse data in HDFS obtained from various data sources and load it in Hive tables.
- Creation of tables, data distribution by implementing partitioning and bucketing, writing and optimizing the HQL queries on Hive data warehouse tool.
- Automate the developed solution using Airflow
- Create Grafana Dashboard using InfluxDB for visualization
- Perform the POC; develop the code and test the code in UAT env & local env using docker container and promote and maintain the code using Git in Production.
- Thoroughly document release procedures and provide training to support team
- Write tests and verify product capabilities
- · Provide training to new joiners

Senior Engineer (Bigdata, Spark, Python)

Dunnhumby

02/2017 - 12/2018

Gurugram, Haryana

IT Analyst (Bigdata, Python, Shell)

Tata Consultancy Services.

08/2014 - 01/2017

Guruqram, Haryana

System Engineer (Shell, SQL, Python)

Tata Consultancy Services.

08/2012 - 08/2014

Gurugram, Haryana

Associate System Engineer (Shell, SQL)

Tata Consultancy Services.

08/2010 - 08/2012

Bangalore, Karnataka

SKILLS, TOOLS & TECHNOLOGIES

Hadoop, Python / Shell Scripting, Impala, SQL, Hive, Google Cloud/ Azure, Sqoop, Spark, Docker, Airflow/Oozie/ControlM, Grafana, Redis/InfluxDB, Oracle, Make/JAM, Git/ACME

EDUCATION

B.Tech. (Computer Science and Engineering)Cochin University (CUSAT), Kochi

08/2006 - 07/2010

70 %

Schooling

C.B.S.E, Delhi

1993 – 2005

Bokaro, India

CERTIFICATIONS

- Microsoft Certified: Azure Fundamentals
- Cloudera Data Analyst, CCA 159 (license ID # 100-023-599)
- ITIL Foundation Exam, APMG In. (Credential # 02999923-01-HQYQ)
- Other Learning Certifications

Honors

- On the Spot Award Clients (Deutsche Bank & American Ex)
- Appreciation Certificate Client (American Ex.)